Guide to the Michelle Madoff Papers, 1969-2013 AIS.1978.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Michelle Madoff Papers
1969-2013
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Madoff, Michelle
AIS.1978.03
7.17 Linear Feet (6 record center boxes, 1 flat box)
Michelle Madoff, an active community volunteer and politician beginning in the 1960s, was concerned primarily with the reduction of air pollution. Her papers consist mostly of published materials relating to environmental topics and related information about citizens' groups created to combat pollution in Pittsburgh. Also included are materials related to her tenure as a member of the Pittsburgh City Council from 1978 to 1993 and her continued environmental activism after retiring from politics.
Biography
Born Pauline Radzinsky in Ontario, Canada, on August 2, 1928, Michelle Madoff was an environmental activist and Politian in Pittsburgh, PA and Arizona. Prior to emigrating to the United States, she changed her name to Michelle Rodin. In 1961, Madoff moved with her husband, Dr. Henry Madoff, and their daughter from Stuyvesant Town, New York City to the Squirrel Hill neighborhood of Pittsburgh. There, she became an active community volunteer and primarily devoted her time to protecting and improving the environment, reducing and monitoring air pollution, and reducing the consumption of energy. In 1969, Madoff founded the Group Against Smog and Pollution (GASP). Later she founded and served as president of Enviro-S.O.S., an environmental group that produced reports on energy concerns and pollution control. Madoff was also involved in determining the future of Jones and Laughlin Steelworks to keep jobs for steel workers in Pittsburgh. She also served as a member of the Pittsburgh City Council from 1978 to 1993 and was active in local and state politics. Madoff later moved to South Carolina and Nevada before settling in Arizona. While living in Nevada, she married Mr. Fred Scheske. She remained active in environmental issues for the remainder of her life. She died on October 12, 2013, at the age of 85 and was survived by Mr. Scheske and a daughter, Karenlin Madoff.
Scope and Content Notes
The Michelle Madoff Papers document her activities as an environmental activist, member of the Pittsburgh City Council, and consultant. Madoff was a member of citizen environmentalist groups in addition to serving in public roles, which is reflected in the overlap of her earlier involvement with Group Against Smog and Pollution (GASP), "Citizens" Environmental Task Force/Enviro-S.O.S., and the Allegheny County Bureau of Air Pollution Control. Madoff's efforts to curb U.S. Steel pollution were a project that transcended her affiliations and were arranged separately. In the mid-1970s, Madoff sought elected office and served four terms in the Pittsburgh City Council. Records from her tenure in City Council mainly comprise of news clippings and her correspondence. The collection also contains many publications about environmental issues of the 1970s, including reports created by her organizations and source materials used in reports and speeches.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Michelle Madoff in 1978. Additional materials were donated by Madoff's husband, Fred Scheske, in 2014.
Previous Citation
Michelle Madoff Papers, 1970-1977, AIS.1978.03, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Madoff, Michelle. Papers, 1970-1977, AIS 78:3, Archives of Industrial Society, University Library System, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Group Against Smog and Pollution (GASP)
II. "Citizens" Environmental Task Force and Enviro-S.O.S.
III. Allegheny County, PA, Bureau of Air Pollution Control
IV. Political Campaigns
V. U.S. Steel
VI. Energy Outlook 1978
VII. Pittsburgh City Council
VIII. GASP-AZ
IX. Personal
X. Photographs
Related Material
Allegheny County Air Pollution Advisory Committee Records, AIS.1992.03, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Allegheny County, Pa. Health Department. Bureau of Air Pollution Control Records, 1941-1978, AIS.1980.04, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Allegheny County Health Department's EPA/SIP Air Quality Program Records, 1968-1985, AIS.1997.30, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Group Against Smog and Pollution (GASP) Records, 1968-2002, AIS.1979.21, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Peter Safar Papers, 1950-2003, UA.90.F102, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Maurice A. Shapiro Environmental Health Collection, 1919-2001, UA.90.F65, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Environment; Environmentalism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; City council members -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Personal papers; Madoff, Michelle
- Group Against Smog and Pollution (GASP), 1969-2011; I.
  Scope and Contents
  Madoff was a founding member of GASP in October 1969 after Pittsburgh's air quality caused asthma attacks severe enough to hospitalize her. The group became a powerful lobby at the state, county, and city levels. This series consists of publications created by GASP and those used for research, correspondence, speeches and testimonies, and ephemera distributed by the group. The series also contains a significant number of news clippings.
  - 35th Anniversary, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Air Pollution Laws, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Allegheny County Conference on Environmental Systems and Service, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Earth Week, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Federal Communications Commission, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - GASP, Brochures, c1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - GASP, Bumper Stickers, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - GASP, Buttons, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - GASP, Correspondence, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - GASP, First Letter, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - GASP, General, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - GASP, Hotline, 1970-2004 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - GASP, Mailings, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - GASP, Red Flag Letter, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Important Speeches & Letters", 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Law Suits - Possible Class Actions, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - League of Conservation Voters, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Environmental Testing Information, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - News Clippings, 1969-2011 (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
  - Nuclear Energy, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Proposals and Grants for GASP, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Second Session of the Conference in the Matter of the Interstate Waters of the Monongahela River and its Tributaries (Pennsylvania, West Virginia, Maryland), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Speeches and Testimonies, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
- Citizens Environmental Task Force and Enviro-S.O.S., 1971-1978; II.
  Madoff founded these groups after stepping down as president of GASP but was still involved with GASP as Advisor on Governmental Affairs. CETF was the parent organization that focused on technical reports on pollution control. Enviro-S.O.S. grew out of CETF to appeal to members of the public with an interest in air quality. This series consists of publications created by CETF and Enviro-S.O.S. and those used for research, correspondence, speeches, and testimonies distributed by the group.
  - Christmas Seal League, 1965-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clean Air Act, Testimony, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Coal Data, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Coke Ovens, 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Committee of Pennsylvania Environmental Groups, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Copyrights, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and Letters to the Editor, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 10-13)
  - Council on Municipal Performance, Report, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - CETF Reports Numbers 1-14, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
  - Energy Costs, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
  - Energy Crisis Position Paper, c 1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - EPA (Environmental Protection Agency), 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - High Density Population Survey, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Jones and Laughlin Steel Company, Clippings, 1970-1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Jones and Laughlin Steel Company, Material and Correspondence Related to Environmental Control, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 25-30)
  - National Clean Air Coalition, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - National Organizations, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - News Clippings, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Publications, 1967-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - Oil Energy, 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - OMB (Office of Management and Budget), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - OSHA (Occupational Safety and Health Administration), 1966-1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Pennsylvania Conference on Steel, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Pennsylvania Environmental Council, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pennsylvania H.B. 1425, 1426, 1427 - Bethlehem Steel, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Scrubbers vs. High Stacks, 1970-1977 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Slag Quenching, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - SOCTAP (Sulfur Oxide Control Technology Assessment Panel), 1973 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sulphates, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Transportation, 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 16-18)
  - Utilities, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Water Pollution, 1970-1976 (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
  - West Penn Power Company, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Allegheny County, PA, Bureau of Air Pollution Control, 1970-1977; III.
  Madoff served as a citizen member of the County's Bureau of Air Pollution Control. The series primarily consists of publications and other sources Madoff used for research purposes during her tenure.
  - Advisory Committee on Air Pollution Control, 1971-1977 (Box 3, Folder 24-27)
  - Advisory Committee on Air Pollution Control, Subcommittee on SO2, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Air Pollution Control, Allegheny County, 1969-1977 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Air Pollution Control, Enforcement, Policing, and Surveillance, 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Air Pollution Control, Illinois, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Air Pollution Control, Indiana, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Air Pollution Control, Pennsylvania, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Air Pollution Emergency Episode Systems, 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Air Pollution Index, Allegheny County, 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Air Pollution Laws in Allegheny County, 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Air Quality Trends - Local, National, Comparative, 1969-1977 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Allegheny County, PA, Air Pollution Variance Board, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 12-12a)
  - Allegheny County, PA, Bureau of Air Pollution Control, 1970-1977 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Allegheny County, PA, Bureau of Air Pollution Control, Article XVIII, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Americans for Energy Independence, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Blast Furnace Slips, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Clean Air Act, 1969-1976 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Clean Air Act, Efforts to Soften, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Duquesne Light, 1970-1977 (Box 4, Folder 19-21)
  - Fugitive Dust Emissions, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Health Effects of Environmental Air Pollutants, Advisory Committee to Study, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Jobs From Pollution Control, 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Monitoring, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Resources, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Pennsylvania H.B. 1333 - Amendment to Air Pollution Control Act, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Source Testing, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - United States Department of the Interior, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Vulcan Materials Company, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Political Campaigns, 1973-1975; IV.
  Madoff unsuccessfully ran for County Commissioner in the mid-1970s. This series documents her first attempt at public office and contains correspondence and campaign materials.
  - Biographical Information and Campaign Material, 1972-1975 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - United Steel Workers of America, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- U.S. Steel, 1957-1977; V.
  Madoff's work regarding U.S. Steel pollution in western Pennsylvania spanned several of the groups in which she was involved. For that reason, records about her U.S. Steel campaigns are arranged in their own series. This series contains documents by and about U.S. Steel's activities regarding air pollution.
  - Clairton Coke Works, GASP Task Force Report, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Clairton Coke Works, Material and Correspondence Relating to Environmental Control, 1957-1977 (Box 5, Folder 5-13)
  - Clairton Coke Works, News Clippings, 1971-1977 (Box 5, Folder 14-16)
  - Clairton Works Agreement, April 1974 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Consent Agreement, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Edward Furia, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Full Page Ads, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Hearing, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Related Notes, 1968-1974 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Mortality Study, June 1976 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Energy Outlook, 1976-1978; VI.
  Energy Outlook 1978 was a reaction to the Energy Crisis. Sponsored by the Allegheny County Bureau of Air Pollution Control, it focused on determining and providing sustainable and renewable energy sources for homes in Greater Pittsburgh. This series contains memoranda and research materials created and used by Madoff.
  - Energy Outlook, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 24-25)
  - "Energy Strategy: The Road Not Taken" by Amory B. Lovins, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - ERDA (Energy Research and Development Administration), 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - National Energy Plan, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Pittsburgh City Council, 1977-2001; VI.
  Madoff served on Pittsburgh City Council from 1978 until 1993. This series contains newspaper clippings, correspondence, proposed ordinances, and campaign materials from Madoff's career as a Council member.
  - Campaign Materials, 1977-1993 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, general, 1978-1993 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, W. G. Diller, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Municipal Record, May 30, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Ordinances, 1980-1988 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - News Clippings, 1978-2001 (Box 6, Folder 1-13)
  - Press Releases, 1981-1986 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Solid Waste Management, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Treasurer Sales, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- GASP-AZ, 2004-2011; VIII.
  After relocating to Arizona, Madoff resumed her community activism against air polluters. This series documents those efforts and contains newspaper clippings, correspondence, and research materials.
  - "Air Quality and Air Monitoring", 2004-2011 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - "Environmental Research", 2001-2007 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - "GASP-AZ", 2007 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - "Gravel Pits", 2007 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - News Clippings, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Promotional Materials, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Photographs, 1967-2013; X.
  This series documents Madoff's activities throughout her career.
  - Allegheny County Bureau of Air Pollution Control, 1968-c1973 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Allegheny County Hearings, c1967-1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Democratic Committee, c1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - GASP Meetings, 1969-1973 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - GASP Promotional, 1969-1972 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Personal, 1967-2013 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Pittsburgh at Night", c1970 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "PIttsburgh at Night (smoggy)", c1970 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, candids, 1978-1993 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, promotional, 1977-1993 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Political Campaigns, 1973-1975 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Personal, 1969-2013; IX.
  This series contains personal correspondence and documents related to Madoff's projects outside of her activist or government activities.
  - Comprehensive Health Planning Association of Western Pennsylvania, 1973-1976 (Box 6, Folder 23-25)
  - Consulting, 1973-1985 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Dance Studio, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - KDKA-AM, contracts, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - KDKA-AM, news clippings, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Personal Correspondence and Clippings, c1958-2011 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Transportation, Squirrel Hill Tunnel, 1968-1973 (Box 6, Folder 31-32)